[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
so when you suggested uh you want to
talk about stoicism your kind of
take on it and what you see what's
representing stoicism and maybe kind of
have a metamodern or developmental lens
what kind of sparked that i guess just
maybe just rift or free associate on
your thoughts in that
that area
i think i'd be curious if i could know a
little bit more about
um for this group of people that are
assembling here at a place called the
stoa
what in terms of stoicism is
familiar and kind of shared and also in
terms of metamodernism so
i can have a sense of how to relate
um so i can kind of speak on the behalf
of maybe the stoic group or the regulars
but in the meantime there's a lot of
faces i don't recognize here so you can
drop them in the chat box i just say
what your
familiar familiarity with stoicism or
metamodernism
i would say that more people at least
the regulars are more familiar with
metamodernism there's book clubs on you
know hanzi's book and stuff like that
than they are
with stoicism um because we hardly have
any events on stoicism here it's sort of
like a space that's stewarded
by a stoic but we don't really talk
about stoicism and i don't know how
sophisticated uh
the understanding is of metamodernism um
as you can see from the chats there's a
bunch of people already dropping down
they're familiar with metamodernism
um but i also imagine there's some
people that are coming in that
might have heard the terms but don't
know much about it so you probably have
a mixed bag of
of understanding here
yeah so i'm definitely not a scholar of
ancient stoic philosophy there's
a number of stoic philosophers that i
have read and appreciated
i actually read them later in life i
grew up more on eastern philosophic
traditions and got into the western
traditions later
but when you're studying vedanta or
buddhism there are ideas that
are very similar to stoic ideas there's
some some things that are quite
different but
some things that are similar in terms of
what is virtue how do you cultivate it
how do you cultivate
increased strength and resilience of
character under adversity how do you
become at peace with death and those
types of things
and uh the actual word stoic
i didn't even know there was a greek
tradition until
i was a bit later and the way that i
heard it was actually a very kind of
simple cartoonish version that i think a
lot of people have heard that just meant
like have a stiff upper lip
and don't show emotions there was um
there was something as i got into
psychotherapy in that community was
actually
completely rejected as this is a way to
fragment yourself and spiritually bypass
and
repress emotionality and emotional
intelligence
and so i think it's very important in
this way when we talk about meta-modern
stoicism
um uh if you read
marcus aurelius or seneca or whatever
they they're not just saying that
simplistic
keep a step flip there they're inquiring
into
um how do we relate with our emotions
and our desires and our thoughts
in a way that moves us in the direction
of what is meaningful and what is
fundamentally meaningful
and so specifically the idea that there
was this relationship between logic and
virtue
uh and so it was both epistemology how
do we do better
clear thinking about the nature of
ourself and reality in the world
and how do we cultivate the qualities of
virtue in ourselves and the positive
relationship between those so the idea
that the true the good and the beautiful
were actually facets of an integrated
reality
it was a emerging from an intuition of
an integrated metaphysics
and i think that's actually something
distinctly different in the greek
enlightenment than in the later european
enlightenment
is um in the later
european enlightenment not as much early
in the renaissance but later
the epistemology section
which got reified with the methods of
science became very much about what is
but in a way that was seen as
fundamentally incommensurable with what
ought
and now of course lots of people had a
sense of an ethics whether it was
the founding fathers being deistic while
being um
you know focused on uh science
but ultimately the the philosophy of
science grounds itself in repeatable
measurements
we measure something we repeat the
measurements we come up with a
you know predictions based on the
hypothesis and so
science formally exists within to study
the objective and the domain of the
simultaneously measurable and repeatable
and that gives is but oh it doesn't
doesn't exist there you have to make
some value statements about what
if we okay a measure can show are we
moving towards or away from but what
should be
which is why the uh the philosophy of
science
by itself tends to orient in a
nihilistic direction
um big bang happened because who knows
why no particular reason
random combinatorics you know et cetera
um
and i think we can actually see a lot of
the problems in the world
through the lens of the is odd
distinction
where science is a
has become an incredibly powerful
epistemology for studying what is
objectively that can then be applied via
technology
to changing what is right and obviously
if
my uh if my choices are
leveraged by intercontinental ballistic
missiles as opposed to arrows
it's a much more powerful leverage to be
able to change
reality but then there's this question
of
well what are we applying the technology
towards what is the world that we
actually want what is worth wanting
and science's opinion is we formally
have no opinion on that
and any position on that is equally
ungrounded because it's not emerging
from something that the methods of
science themselves can validate
and so then well what ends up funding
the research
is what's going to have return on
investment so basically capital returns
and more generally game theory ends up
being the thing so then
the nihilism of social darwinism becomes
the because good basically becomes what
wins at game theory
and that's a very not only superficial
but eventually self-terminating
definition of good
so um so yeah when i think about
stoicism i think about
deep contemplation on what is actually
good what is desirable what's worth
desiring
basically a reified ethics and
a reified epistemology and is there a
unified metaphysics from which those can
both arise
as a basis of how do we do choice making
and ultimately that's the thing
is how to inform human choice towards an
effective life individually and
collectively at different scales
something that
i'm focused on a lot right now is uh the
collective scale
since the beginning of what we call
civilization like early
egypt sumeria whatever
a tiny percentage of all the people that
have ever lived
lived in democracies or republics lived
in a system that had any kind of
participatory
governance almost everybody lived under
feudalism or monarchy or some kind of
autocratic control
and the few times that democracies or
republics
occurred they occurred following a
cultural enlightenment
and it was a cultural enlightenment that
had to do a couple things
it had to do something in both is and
ought
and specifically in the is space it had
to get objective and intersubjective so
i'll say what i mean by that
we see the athenian democracy coming out
of kind of a greek enlightenment
and the greek enlightenment was
everybody should learn logic
and learn history and learn math and
learn rhetoric and learn the arts and
if you have a high value on education
where everyone can
assess base reality on their own not
just say what someone else said because
you know the great authority in the past
said it but everyone can actually assess
space reality on their own
then you have the unifying capab the
unifying nature of reality itself
and the other key part was the socratic
method the socratic dialectic where
everyone could take everyone else's
perspective
and position in the european
enlightenment later it was the hegelian
dialectic and the kind of methods of
science but if everyone can assess base
reality on their own
and they can take each other's
perspective they end up being like we
don't need rulers we can actually have
conversations and be able to bring about
self-governance
um but there also did have to be a
shared culture they all emerged
that cultural enlightenment valued those
things right and it also had some other
ideas of what is good that it values
same with the founding of this country
and
notice i got some feedback all right
um and
so most everyone can sense that the u.s
has
been undergoing radical decay and it
feels like it's kind of near the
end of like being much of anything
and democracy's never made it past 300
years we're 250 years currently
i think it'd be good if everybody was
unmute
yeah i'm just going to force everyone on
mute and then i'm gonna
ask you to unmute yourself there you go
all right um
and so the
the cultural enlightenment i i'm going
a bit off topic but but it tells you how
i'm thinking about it
um george washington and the founding of
this country said
that the number one goal of government
should be the comprehensive education of
every citizen in what he called the
science of government
basically everyone needed educated about
how humans work and how human
coordination works well enough
that they can really participate and
jefferson said if i could have perfect
news in a broken government or perfect
government broken news i take perfect
news because if people understand the
world they live in they can
overthrow the corrupt government and
make sense of things and coordinate
but i think the key thing there is that
collective choice making requires
collective sense making
and collective perspective taking i have
to be able to understand how other
people are seeing things
to then be able to work on strategies
that are effective together so
i think either kind of the
decay that's happened in the us and
other places continues and
many areas of the world have already
moved back to more autocratic governance
we see that happening in brazil and
venezuela and turkey and
all over we see it's already happened
largely in russia and china
if we want something other than
autocracy and autocracy is easier
because it's easier for a small number
of people at the top to coordinate than
for a large number of people to
coordinate and i actually don't think
it's possible for a very large number of
people to coordinate
without something like an enlightenment
at the basis where those people can all
actually make sense of reality well they
can regulate their emotions enough that
they're not just being limbically
hijacked
and they can take each other's
perspectives and do
higher order synthesis and so
[Music]
now when we come to the concept of
metamodern so there was kind of
the greek enlightenment could be thought
of as a pre-modern enlightenment we
could think of the european
enlightenment as
modernity and it was an epistemology
of that allowed us to actually produce
and build things better right newton's
calculus
caught on not because people
aesthetically liked it but because it
aimed canons much better than pendulum
dowsing did so those who took
took it on actually game theoretically
won
um so modernity brought the capacity to
build
the world but it also brought
the ability to destroy environments and
oppress the world more effectively
so then post-modernism of course was
a bunch of largely valid critiques
of the problems of modernity but without
it was deconstruction but without a new
reconstruction for how to build so then
basically the only thing it can do
is critique building and which is a
entropic direction
so the meta-modern idea which i'm sure
everyone's familiar with is is there an
epistemology that can take the relevant
critiques of post-modernism and actually
factor them into a better
better modernity or meta-modernity that
is a
in it has to be an integrated
epistemology of how do we do production
and building and
towards what ends are actually
meaningful
and so when i think of meta modern
stoicism i think of
uh both
it to be able to solve any of the
problems of the world right now
we need better participatory governance
that can understand the problems and
work on solutions at all and
the basis of that will be people that
can make sense of reality better
make sense of each other's perspectives
and actually coordinate
those are some initial thoughts since we
started from a random place
so maybe maybe i'll start here and uh
for people listening if you have
questions start throwing them in the
chat box have like a question
uh so i can i can fish for them because
a lot of the comments in the
chat box um you mentioned something when
we were chatting on whatsapp about
uh what your current take was on
how stoicism is being presented uh today
in you know uh the popular culture and
how it's being kind of
repurposed by certain i guess maybe
masculine or self-help
help kind of gritted out type type folks
so the question is do i have a critique
of
the modern presentation of stoicism
either a critique on how modern
socialism is presented or just what your
thoughts on
on how it's currently being presented i
don't have that many
um i i don't feel like i know the
current
modern stoic authors very well i know a
few things that seem like they have some
elements right and some
fairly superficial um one thing i'll say
is that
the superficial understanding of
stoicism that looks a little bit like
logic over emotions and a kind of
decrease of the value of emotion
um or emotional intelligence um
on one side and then the kind of
let's call it trauma aware perspective
that
pays more attention to what the effect
of unexpressed unfelt unintegrated
feelings are shadow work gestalt work
whatever i would say that's a fake
dialectic
or a fake dichotomy um i
the two things that you don't ever want
to do with emotions is
immediately act out on them or repress
them
right and those are both dysfunctional
activities you want to be able to
notice them arising and recognize
they're arising for a reason that has
signal for you to understand
there's there's actual intelligence and
signal in every emotional response
so i want to be able to see it and
really be with it and look at it which i
can't do if i'm shaming it or wishing it
wasn't there
but for my own internal inquiry into my
own wholeness not immediately acting on
it to then see what is the right
response
and sometimes the right response is to
say that thing to that person sometimes
the right response is to change the
meaning i'm making
cbt style sometimes it's to recognize
that an old trauma keeps getting
triggered and being projected on current
events and i actually have to go work
with that
[Music]
so another part of how i think about the
valuable thing
that we can associate with stoicism is
a philosophy that asks how can i relate
to this
in a way that increases my empowerment
to relate to life with more agency
um i think empowerment is
we can think about ennoblement right
what are my virtues and how do i
if i wasn't just asking what's in it for
me if i wasn't asking what is easy and i
was asking
how would someone that i respect the
most behave what would that look like
and why is it that i respect that so i'm
mining my
own value system and then i'm noticing
the delta
between my value system and how i'm kind
of conditioned to show up and i'm asking
how do i close that delta that's a very
deep
interesting inquiry but as much as there
is the kind of
deepening virtue and enabling there's
also the how do i relate to this in a
way that empowers me that i can continue
to relate to life
with more capacity to be in service to
what i care about
and uh i think it's a very important
question when it comes to
emotions and difficulty of um
there's a there's a kind of intelligence
that is different than cognitive
intelligence which is kind of um
power intelligence or agentic
intelligence and
if those aren't bound together you can
develop power that is not bound to
virtue that ends up being quite
destructive
but if you develop virtue that isn't
bound to power it's basically impotent
um so how you have
virtue wisdom power all co-developed
in so you're capable of service and know
what you're in service to
is the thing that i think is actually
interesting and worth exploring
cool um so we have a lot of questions
now so i'll
pivot to the chat box um and i'll
give everyone the opportunity to unmute
themselves so use this power
with wisdom um pranab you had a question
if you can unread yourself and ask it to
daniel
yeah so uh thanks for this talk it's
awesome so far
you scroll up to the question
um yeah so basically what are some ways
that you think
metamodernism or at least the
epistemology um
hymenomonarism can be taught
or kind of encouraged within oneself
within dialogue with another person or
within
scale like at a community or society
basis
i'll share a few things but it'll be
more like a couple random smatterings
than a comprehensive addressing of the
the pedagogy because how i would answer
that
for kindergartners versus high schoolers
and for people with different levels of
investment and existing familiarity is
obviously going to be quite different
but
[Music]
a couple things in the academy there has
been this
major divide most of the time between
the liberal arts and the sciences
between something that orients
more towards uh interpersonal
intelligence
versus or inter-subjective versus
objective empirical
but to make sense of society you deeply
need both working together
you need to be able to understand what
other people believe why they believe it
and what's the actual signal in that
and what base reality regarding
objective things are
so to be oriented to both empiricism and
being able to understand other people's
narratives simultaneously
is a key part so some processes for how
to do that
take anything in the world that you're
trying to sense make or that someone's
trying to sense me and trying to help
them with it
and one thing i would have them do is
say okay find
all the narratives that make sense of
this that are out there what are the
primary narratives it's like the mimetic
tribes or kind of narrative
generating clusters right so if i'm
trying to make sense of the india china
war i'm trying to make sense of the
blm protests there's obviously um
conspiracy narratives far right moderate
right
antifa whatever so i would try to
generate the narrative landscape so i
say what are the ways that different
humans are making sense of this
and then i would try to steal man all
the arguments i would try to actually
find the very strongest version of each
of those narratives
and make it as reified as possible so
that i really understand
why they're understanding that and that
i can look for the signal in it because
there's never no signal
then i would use some propositional
logic and break the narrative into
individual propositions
right so a narrative is always that so
the bricks were put there by this for
this purpose the cops did this whatever
it is break down the propositions
and then i would look for what evidence
do those groups give to support each of
the propositions and what can what sense
can i make of that evidence
and what additional evidence can i find
and i would seek to both try to
verify and falsify each proposition
and then stepping while acknowledging
that i might not be able to verify or
falsify i might just be able to say this
is a
proposition for which i i can't really
ground it one way or the other at all
and all i can do is sit in some
uncertainty and ask questions around
where the burden of proof should be
so this is why peter was talking about
comfort with uncertainty
earlier if i'm not comfortable with
uncertainty
then i'm going to rush to premature
certainty and just be wrong about
stuff i have to be comfortable with
uncertainty to be able to
do the epistemics necessary to come up
with appropriate certainty but the
comfort with uncertainty doesn't mean
that i don't
want increasing certainty right it
doesn't mean that there isn't curiosity
in an epistemic drive
that wants to figure shit out it's that
i don't want to believe shit without
having gone through the appropriate
process
to have the right calibrated confidence
margin it also means i never
make what is most sacred to me attached
to that belief system where now i can't
change it
right because the confidence margin will
always be less than a hundred percent
this is the way i interpret the the
first verse of the tao dae ching
saying the knowledge that's knowable is
not the eternal knowledge the doubt that
is speakable it's not the eternal doubt
your best
i might have high confidence margin on
something but there's some shit that's
in the unknown unknown that i'm not even
aware i don't know about that could
change the framing or the context
of the whole thing and if i make what is
most sacred to me or my identity
based on believing this thing because i
have high confidence i just became
biased in a way that keeps me from being
connected to life or learning
so i i might have a high enough
confidence to inform action which i need
but i also need that i can ongoingly be
able to change my mind
this is also how i take the judaic that
shall have no false idols
and that every model of reality is an
idol right
every model of reality isn't actually
reality so i'm going to construct a
model
that is a radical information
compression and reduction on the actual
reality that
hopefully will be useful but is never
actually true
and when i know that i'm i i don't ever
make my model sacred right so i can
always change and update my models
and i don't ever become destroyed when
that happens because
i actually have a relationship beyond
cognition
with myself and reality right what is
sacred what is the doubt
um and a reverence for
reality that if i'm ever wrong i fucking
want to see it
right because i want to be in the
intimacy of being with reality as much
as possible
um so teaching people
how to
uh make sense of the current world by
being able to see how everyone else
makes sense of it
to really seek to take their
perspectives and make their arguments
well
and then to seek to do analysis on each
of the parts
to calibrate confidence appropriately to
both
to not pretend to have no bias in which
case your bias will just be hiding from
you but to take all the biases
i'm going to try to falsify this now i'm
going to try to verify it so i can do
both sides of a dialectic and then to
step back
after the analysis and be able to look
at the whole thing and say
what higher order perspectives are
possible from looking at this whole
thing
and what additional information would we
need to be able to go further
this is one way of being able to help
people
learn how to think better
i could give lots and lots of examples
like this becomes a very rich topic and
we start to get into what should the
future of education look like but also
what should the future of a civilization
imagine that we built a civilization
where the goal of it was evolving the
humans in it maximally
right and we had some congruent sense of
what that was where the nature of
how work happened and how information
was shared how the algorithms on the
internet were structured was towards
that it would
be very interesting nora bateson's warm
data stuff is very good i know she's
coming on for helping people be able to
understand complexity in a relatively
simple way
forests egp forest landers egp if that
comes on is a very good system to get
people to ask
much much better questions including
questions that they didn't even know
were things
thank you just to piggyback on that um
i'm designing a session for rebel wisdom
on friday on thursday about memetic
mediation
and we're going to like play different
videos of like trump aoc
all these political medic tribes and
then
process it emotionally first before we
inquire to the propositions
do you think it's that the exercise that
you mapped out about looking at the
narratives do you think that could also
be
repurposed for some kind of emotional
integration work
so there's a few ways that i would i
mean pro
noticing the emotions and giving some
space to process them means that they
won't be
covertly hijacking your sense-making
because you've made them overt so that's
awesome
right um if i know that i'm angry or i
know that i'm scared i can actually
look for how that's affecting my sense
making and in
complex scenarios it's very rarely
like a simple equation how anything
works
in all societal and ecology and
psychology things are complex it's
usually that there's a hundred different
causal factors that are changing
and nexus causation enough stuff happens
to move something across a threshold
so what happens why two people who both
have expertise in climate change and are
earnestly trying to figure it out can
come to such different senses or
on immunity or anything complex is
because they
weight the variables differently
intuitively without realizing they're
doing it
they recognize these are all variables
but their life experience has them
weight some of them more than others
and so to notice our own waiting that's
where bias usually shows up
and the emotions are a very interesting
way to start to be able to look at it
so if i'm looking at trump and aoc and
whatever
i might have emotion come up because
of having adopted enough in-group
out-group type of stuff that i'm just
responding
group out group group think triggered
kind of stuff and i want to be able to
and this is why you actually have to
have a virtue
the the stoicism kind of idea you have
to have a virtue
that has you not just think that's a
good idea
right because lots of people would be
like yes i've accepted in groupout group
because my site is right and the other
sides are wrong and fuck them and like
this is time to pick sides and be strong
and be at war
so to be able to say hey before
having high certainty in anything i want
to actually make sure i'm taking all the
biases and that i actually have clear
understanding of the thing i'm willing
to take a stand on shit but i want to
make sure that i'm actually thinking and
seeing clearly first
and i can't do that if i only have
pejorative straw man versions of the
other people
if i've never actually been able to
sense why they would come to that in a
way that isn't pejorative
um so if you have a value around that
around saint francis seek first to
understand before seeking to be
understood you
then you will do the work towards it so
i might be emotional because of those
reasons and i get to see oh wow i have
bought into
a particular chunk of rhetoric right
actually there's a narrative warfare
happening and it won and it captured me
and made me a narrative soldier and i
thought i
was choosing a free will and not really
uh where those people's perspective
strikes me as existentially risky so
much that i can't listen to them
right them them not being willing to
wear masks means that they are science
denying flat earth grandma killers and
they're going to ruin everything
and or whatever it is right them
wanting to wear mask means that they've
bought into the pedo
deep state and want to rfid chip my kids
and
so i can't actually hear anything
outside of that
narrative frame that i've already
accepted so that's one thing the
emotions might give me
another thing they might give me that's
even deeper is
okay so i'm looking at homelessness or
amazon destruction or whatever and i
feel really fucking sad
because the sadness is showing me
something that's actually sacred to me
or i'm angry or i'm afraid any of the
negative emotions are actually showing
me something sacred to me
the anger is i'm seeing something sacred
and i'm looking at who's
who's violating it i'm focused on the
blame side but what
the basis of it is is there something i
love and care about
that if i didn't there would be no
emotional energy of anything i wanted to
protect or that i cared was being harmed
i'd just be like yeah fuck i cut the
amazon i don't give a shit
i'm only angry because there's something
i actually really care about so if i
trace the fear or the anger or the
sadness back to
what is it that is actually sacred to me
that i'm trying to be in service of
that's a helpful piece of intelligence
then i can say
okay so i know what is sacred to me i
want to be in best service to
it do i understand what is harming it or
could harm it well enough that i can
come up with solutions
if not can i seek to understand better
that i can actually be effective
and what way of relating to these
emotions helps me be in most
service so if i hold the sadness in a
way that decreases my agency i just get
overwhelmed and depressed and crippled
i'm actually
not in service to what i care about and
so the stoic what is it that empowers me
is to say
if i actually care about that i have the
care can't be impotent
right the love can't be impotent it has
to actually be able to act and be in
service to what's cared about
so how can i relate to this that most
empowers me to be an effective service
towards what is sacred to me
yeah yeah that's really good i think
that
okay um oh man
so many questions benita roy you sent me
a question privately
uh if you're going to mute yourself ask
it to daniel
uh
hey bonnie hi see you um
so thank you for for being you
my question is
where does this kind of analysis
and epistemic precision
where does does where what is the
boundary of that does that fit
it obviously it fits in this world
situation
but does it fit in your personal life
like
like like and how does that meld through
because most of us don't have the kind
of mind
the kind of capacity you have and
we want to take that part of what you're
offering
and meld that into our personal lives
i i is that is that a question that you
can understand so far
yeah that's a great question actually
i think it's most important for most
people there and actually easiest
because
our personal live situations don't have
the same level of complexity as
all the things connected to climate
change fortunately so we don't have to
have
expert level skills in 24 different
fields to
understand why our partner feels the
thing they feel
um yeah so my personal life
seek first to understand before seeking
to be understood is as deep a piece of
wisdom as anything i've ever heard
and it's not complicated
it's simple it's only hard when the ego
gets hijacked and really fucking wants
to say what it wants to say
and so there has to be a value around
i actually don't want that hijacked ego
place to get to run me
now i'm not going to in order to be
effective towards it
there are certain ways of repressing it
that just make it worse i want to
actually be able to understand how it
arises why it arises what its hooks are
how i work with those
so that i can actually become more
empowered
but ultimately that's the place that
when it talks i feel
regret and shame afterwards and need to
apologize there are other places that i
feel
the deepest kind of pride afterwards
because i feel that i lived aligned with
my own deepest values and there's more
integration
i want to pay attention to which of
those places is actually
um growing in its empowerment which ones
i'm feeding
and so
uh like my wife and i have
a few guidelines that are very helpful
one is
um both people are never upset at the
same time
and if so we take a break so that if
if she's upset i don't go into my own
emotional reaction on her emotional
reaction where we're just spiraling and
no one is actually clear to be able to
bring it up where
then i'm not able to hear her i'm just
hearing how what she says is wrongly
blaming me
and what it means for me and whatever
there's no capacity in the relationship
in that moment for
good things to happen so if she brings
something up i want to be able to come
from enough wholeness that i don't
instantly have to make it about me and i
can actually hear her experience
and then i can help find out what does
she need to be able to feel
better to feel heard to return to center
and then if i have something i'd like to
process
afterwards when she's clear and has
capacity i say hey can we talk about
this she's like yeah
so um and
often times the thing that i wanted to
say before seeking to understand
after i seek to understand i don't even
want to say it was wrong
or i understand where they were coming
from enough that i have a different
perspective on the thing
um
[Music]
being able to notice the place
that wants to speak
when out of center and like the
addiction that it is to want to do that
and to be able to just witness it like
you know when you meditate and your nose
itches and you don't itch it
there's this very helpful thing of just
being able to say i don't have to act on
every sensation that arises i can
witness it
and i don't have to act on the sensation
of i need to fucking be right and
tell them why i'm right and whatever
right now i can just
if if the thing i'm going to say is
really true it'll still be true tomorrow
if it is emotionality that uh will kind
of blow over
well then i can say but only when i'm
angry do i have the courage well just
choose to have more courage so that in a
centered place you'll still say the
thing that is true
so for me i'm wondering i mean
actually just came up now it's like
i wonder if we could take what you just
said which was beautiful
see the pattern in it
and say that's the same pattern
practically
at this larger scale because it has
it has deep feeling in that pattern
i have no idea what i'm saying right now
but like
like instead of like over here i'm like
this and over here i'm like that
does this pattern somehow
i don't know yeah no i like it because
there's a question of is the thing that
i'm describing at the macro scale kind
of dry and sterile
because in my relationship it's not dry
and sterile it's very
yeah i wouldn't say dry and sterile i
would say is
hyperinformed so so i'm not trying to be
for
pejorative it's hyperinformed that's
that's important that's important
we we need that and i'm wondering where
like the dances
between like because in you
it's coherent we know it's coherent
because it's coherent in daniel
schmartenberger
there's the evidence
you see what i'm well saying think in
terms of the significantly informed
like one way that i i'll i'll tell you
an epistemic tool that i use to
calculate confidence margins where it
really matters
i and this is like a a set of formal
systems from information theory
um so
i look at a situation and try to say how
many orders of magnitude of interactions
in the network diagram are occurring um
if it's an ecosystem
maybe you know we have some basis of
being able to say at what level of
action this is always hard because the
question is where is the boundary
because
i could say it's the whole fucking
universe for everything which is
ultimately true
but i have to say at which nexus
causation is being
very significantly informed i'm looking
at what 10 to the 12 orders of magnitude
of complexity in this situation or
whatever
then i want to look at the various
hypotheses
narrative as a set of hypotheses and
look at the various hypotheses
and be able to say what data do i have
that supports it what do i have that
either supports
a mutually exclusive hypothesis or
directly refutes it
and i want to take that down i want to
use information compression to say what
is the
least number of bits in which i can
represent that
so then i get to see the total unique
pieces
of the unique bits of information
supporting the hypothesis
the unique bits of information refuting
it but also the total number of bits of
information
i have relative to the complexity of the
scenario so even if i have 10x more
supporting than refuting but the total
amount of info i have is tiny relative
to the complexity my confidence will be
low
so this this sounds like a very
logical process which isn't necessarily
what it feels like and if i'm talking
with my wife right
um but that's because the total amount
of complexity in the situation with my
wife is just not
climate change right like it's
it's uh i actually want to be hyper
informed
there it's just easier right i want to
understand
what is she thinking why is she feeling
that way what brought it
you know what brought it about what
needs feel unmet for her what would
actually
feel meaningful and so i'm seeking to be
hyperinformed there and it's not
hyperinformed i'm seeking to be
adequately informed
that i'm in touch with reality
um and then once i'm like oh i get it i
get
where she's coming from and i guess why
she feels the way she is and why she's
expressing that then i feel like i can
start to navigate
but i can't navigate when i don't have
the map at all yet
yeah so just so we're on the same page
hyperinformed is not a pejorative
like i think i think that's like well it
could be
but for you you're like hyperinformed
you put that book aside and then you
like act in a feeling sense so
um i'm gonna say something really crazy
like i don't even
i don't even i don't even like what i'm
gonna say
okay so um
what if we take that kind of action
logics with your wife
and put it to like ecology in the earth
and have the ace and the hole
are hyper-informed reality
which i actually think you do
like there's a kind of loving of the
earth in the
in the life force that's more like the
actual logics you have with your wife
and then you have this hyperinformed
what if we could communicate that
i think i think that's the point right
yeah
so i see that all in you
well i mean in all of us
when we were talking about binding
wisdom virtue and power
we can that's almost like uh three
chakras depending upon how you want to
define it right
and you could take the chakra system or
any ancient system that
was trying to explore this as like if i
think about
the piece of hindu artwork if i think
about uh
the hindu chakra system as each of them
representing a different type of
intelligence
the growth of the person was
to develop all of them and all of them
in relationship with each other so the
whole being could be in a full
relationship with the whole of reality
and so there's a different kind of
intelligence like the
and whether they actually have any
relationship to parts of the body
because of endocrine glands or nerves
doesn't matter to at least have it be a
metaphorical system
um but the the will or the power there's
a kind of intelligence to say what way
of me relating to this most
increases my capacity to serve what i
care about
right there's a kind of intelligence
that's asking that that is different
than asking
what is what am i able to falsify or
verify
about objective reality which is also
different than the kind of intelligence
of asking or hear how would i
communicate this in a way that would
land for someone and in order to have it
land for them i have to actually be them
right there's a kind of empathy built in
that i have to be them to know how to
lend or try to
which is different than what is most
sacred to me and so
i think what we're what we're interested
in
is how do we develop whole people that
have all of their intelligences online
and all of them working together
analysis and synthesis logic and
intuition
and then that are in relationship with
all of reality there aren't
race issues and environmental issues and
economic issues there's reality issues
where all of those things are
inextricably interconnected and
interconnected to
the being of all the other people and
when we have increasingly whole people
in
an increasingly integris relationship
with the wholeness of reality we start
getting much better
processes i think that's related to what
you're saying
thank you very much thank you ronnie it
was really fun
thank you benita as always um
david you had a question that got up
lots
of plus ones if you can unmute yourself
and ask it
[Music]
hi peter hi daniel
um i wanted to keep this question kind
of a little bit
broad and vague and that is just around
so daniel you had an experience being
psychological
uh guide and support and you saw these
people presenting
their view of their small world and the
big world uh and that
sounded like that informed your own
growing awareness and
investigations at the time and i'm
curious if the
murder of burdens that you would have
seen in your
patients or just in friends um
informed you in any way and if you could
speak to that
the neurodivergence in particular as
opposed to
yeah so so in in the sense that i
imagine someone can come across stoicism
at an
early age and develop with that
framework in mind and then someone might
be
further along the spectrum and that
might also influence their
their information uptake or whatever you
want to call it
so are you asking how much people were
able to
grow and change and develop based on
uh what types of
previous experience
yes to that but also more to the point
of
in the case of say autism or something
like that where we have this
this awareness of a spectrum um how much
did you see that impact their awareness
of this
reality that you personally also see
and then also their ability to latch on
to
different information as well
yeah clearly not everyone is
equally capable of every kind of
process and there is development that
everyone can do and everyone's not even
equally capable of every type of
development
right like down syndrome is a real thing
that affects
uh capability in in certain ways autism
is kind of interesting because autism is
not
the spectrum that we have now where such
a high percentage of people are
considered somewhere on the spectrum as
a relatively
new evolutionary phenomena i don't think
it's evolutionary i think it's
cultural and environmental um
and in some ways it just represents
lack of development like not having a
like we can look at all the physiologic
dynamics right we can look at ubiquitous
sugar and
um psych meds
starting early and things that damage
the microbiome and glyphosate and
ubiquitous mold toxins and whatever that
are the result of you know
post-industrialized life and say
uh there's actual physiologic elements
that have happened but there's no
one-for-one thing
it is basically a much more complex set
of dysregulations of homeodynamics that
express in a dysregulated nervous system
that's true there's also
[Music]
let's say it's people growing up as
digital natives with a lot of screen
time
where they're getting much faster
dopaminergic hits
from activities that are decoupled from
the movement of their body and decoupled
from accomplishing things in an
evolutionary sense it starts to actually
mess up the nature of
the dominance and process of
neurotransmission there's a lot of
things that go in
there's also like that's actually an
example of
things that would develop certain
capacities just being underdeveloped
because we're they're not actually
having a a culture or an upbringing that
develops some of those things
um so for instance if i have like this
is a common
understanding but if i have toys that do
fucking everything
and i'm not making a stick into certain
toys and i rock into certain toys
there's certain kinds of creativity that
don't develop because i don't actually
have
i have so much external other market
creativity that is just creating
dopaminergic response
i don't have to do curiosity creativity
and exploration to find my own
so there's a lot of places where the
world structure is simply not developing
shit in people that
it needs to um
i also think that there's you know we
can think about
development from an individual
perspective and also from a group
selection
perspective and
the idea that everyone is going to
evolve to the highest stages of
development on all lines of development
is
silly this is not going to happen and in
the same way that not everyone is going
to be
come masterful at every language and
every scientific discipline and every
musical instrument
and so um
[Music]
there's also a question around like what
is the minimum competence of certain
kinds of capacities that are needed to
engage as a citizen
where then i can be part of a collective
intelligence
that orients that the people who are
best at different things are able to
differentially contribute to those
things
i don't know if that addressed the
question because
the question as you said was kind of
broad i'm happy to take another step at
it if you want
i think that did it address the question
i mistakenly forgot to include
um how something like uh stoicism might
impact
um the path that these people might take
and your own thoughts around that and
maybe if you could speak to your own
experiences
in i can't remember if it was counseling
or more clinical psychology
the people that are obviously clearly
functional
and just define themselves as mildly on
the spectrum or mildly aspie which is
it's basically an increasingly large
identifier for
things that really should not be
considered a disease diagnosis it's just
people who kind of suck at certain
things or who never learn something or
who just are introverted or
whatever but the the patterns that we
think of as kind of mildly aspie
one way you could think of them is
[Music]
low low capacity for nuance
we can talk about it as low empathy and
interpersonal
recognition but a major part of it is
for nuance so they usually end up
becoming very good at things that are
black and white like whether it's
computer programming or
mechanical engineering or things like
that and so stoicism
implemented without nuance uh
can can be pretty clunky and messed up
just like any
like any because the
the eternal dao cannot be spoken
the version that i speak will be wrong
and so
uh i can write down here here are the
virtues and here's the code of behavior
and then someone else who doesn't really
get the spirit of it they're getting the
letter of the law without the spirit of
it will implement it in a
fundamentalist righteous kind of way
with without being able to understand in
ecclesiastes when it said there's a time
to kill and a time to heal and to sow
and to reap and for every purpose under
heaven
well how do i know which time it is for
which of the things well there is no
absolute algorithm for that that's being
able to use all of those types of
intelligence with full presence and
discernment
to a set of values that can't be
formally explicated there's a girdle's
theorem here
where what is meaningful is beyond
formal explication
but there if i have a formal explication
it'll work lots of times but then
there'll be a place at which i'm like no
that's actually wrong
what is it in me that can recognize when
the code is wrong
that's the thing we want to be
developing in people which is their
actual capacity for discernment
and where people don't have that as much
we want to be developing it where
there's upper bounds for physiologic
reasons
then we would want a good society that
puts them in
roles they get to or supports them to be
in roles they get to
utilize the capacities they do have well
without being damaged by the ones they
don't
thank you daniel that that fit with my
my my thoughts around that is
as well thanks
all right uh hannah you had a follow
question
i will paste it again in the chat box
yeah um so i wanted to
look at this topic from another angle i
am an anxious person and i have panic
attacks
so hearing a lot of language that i
think has developed from
looking at things like triggered and
limbic states and so on
makes me wonder will it be more
challenging
for me to learn these sorts of skills
or maybe will my familiarity
with things like panic attacks actually
be helpful here
and you know what is going to be a good
way for people like me to approach this
beautiful question uh i used to have
panic attacks
um i had a period where that was quite
debilitating and
didn't sleep for quite a long time and
um so
so i i understand um
early i had a completely debilitating
fear of public speaking where i just
couldn't like i would pass out if i
tried
[Music]
um
i only found one thing
that actually really worked for panic
attacks
um and by worked i mean
actually changed the underlying reality
fundamentally as opposed to managed it
[Music]
i didn't find that cbt did or dbt
or hitting pillows or emotional release
therapy or gestalt or hypnotherapy
like those were all cool but i or breath
work or meditation or
the only thing that i found worked was a
there are different ways of doing it but
they're ways that go into the panic
attack as opposed to away from it
and so i'll explain the mechanism here
briefly
a panic attack is different than just
generalized anxiety
right it's generalized anxiety that
turns into a feedback loop
and so let's say that i'm
anxious about some shit everybody's
anxious like that fear is a
natural part of life and we'll feel some
adrenaline happen and we know that
that's because
in evolutionary environments the fear
usually needed a physiologic response so
some adrenaline would come so i could
run or fight or something
now most of the things i'm afraid of
don't actually need adrenaline because
i'm not going to have a
physical response to if the teacher
likes my
um report or if the person on the date
wants to respond or not
and as a result i don't use up that
adrenaline there isn't a kind of
adaptation it just feels shitty right
and
so maybe i'm in a situation where
i have a relationship that's going bad
and i'm not sure if it's going to work
or not
and i'm not sure if they're being honest
to me and then finances are also tight
and something else i start to have
more base anxiety so my base anxiety
gets higher than us
and then maybe at a certain point
something happens and my base anxiety is
high enough that
the sensation of it inside of me the the
fluttering in my stomach or the like
hotness in my ears or in my face
all of a sudden is a sensation that i'm
unfamiliar with
like it's at a higher level and all of a
sudden i get scared of that sensation
because i'm like what's happening am i
dying what's
like am i going crazy what the fuck's
happening now when i get afraid of my
own
experience of fear now i'm in a feedback
loop because i'm not afraid of reality
i'm afraid of my own experience of fear
so my body produces adrenaline to the
symptoms of adrenaline
and that tight feedback loop is a
motherfucker because sometimes it'll
just produce adrenaline
to the symptoms of adrenaline so then
the symptoms get worse so then you get
more scared and it does that until you
just run out of adrenaline and
eventually pass out or you
go get a benzo or an alcohol or
something
if i try to do breath work to comment
which of course to some degree i can't
because i can
take breaths and stimulate my
parasympathetic nervous system and in
our inverse to a sympathetic drive and
if i try to distract myself with bunny
videos or whatever
i would do to try to create a different
response i'm still
affirming that i'm scared of that
sensation
and that i don't want it to happen and
that if it comes i'll be scared of it so
my
my sympathetic adrenal complex is still
oriented to produce adrenaline to my
symptoms of adrenaline
so i'm always scared of that thing
happening so
there are processes where you get
facilitated to go
into the panic attack fully and
so you start to think about things
you're anxious of you start to feel the
symptoms and then you start to say
it's important to know that it can't
kill you even if you feel like you can't
breathe that worse you pass out the
panic attack is gone when your conscious
mind isn't there you start breathing
again so you know
this is just sensations and as
uncomfortable as they are they can't
actually hurt me
they're just fucked up feeling but
sensations
you're like ultimately i want to
understand myself i want to understand
what's arising enough that i can
actually be with myself and
and have more wholeness so then you
start to
go into a process where you say all
right
and typically i would say this should be
facilitated and i can recommend
processes that do that so you go into a
process where the
you're being facilitated to
notice the symptoms the rapid heart the
flushing face
and rather than want them to go away
welcome them
say i welcome all of this i want to feel
it in fact i want to feel the fullness
of it i want to understand all of it and
be with all of it so
not only do i want to feel it i want it
to get as intense as it can
so you actually welcome it to let the
heart racing get more intense the
difficulty breathing getting more
intense
and you can't say it while actually
really wishing it goes away you have to
really lean in as an explorer as a
curious explorer to be like what is this
when that happens there is a clear
signal to your adrenals that you're not
afraid of the thing you're leaning into
and it stops producing adrenaline in
response to the symptoms of adrenaline
you're there is a kind of hpa access
neurological reset
psychological reset as well and
then once you've done that several times
you start to be like
actually i'm not afraid of this thing i
can lean into it i'm not going to die
i'm not going to go crazy i can
and and the feelings are actually
whatever right they're not that terrible
and then the key becomes well you'll be
afraid for it to come on at certain
times
like i okay i don't want it to come on
when i'm having to give my talk or
with my work or whatever it is so then
you actually have to welcome that it can
come
anytime because otherwise the time that
it isn't welcome is when you'll still be
in that response
and be like okay if it comes at that
time i'll be with it
i'll go into it i'll be with it because
what the fuck else am i gonna do like i
don't really have much any other good
choices
and this is the process of leaning in
and actually befriending the fear so
fear stops being a self-reinforcing loop
anyone who goes through that and
actually goes through it
will have both a level of compassion and
humility
plus a level of strength that is not
really available if people haven't gone
through it
any follow-up question hannah uh
many follow-up thoughts uh that i will
process slowly over time uh thank you
daniel
that was really useful hammockaway.com
is a site
that has some good information on a
process like this
and that they may even have a list of uh
practitioners
and this is a big part of stoicism of
wanting to really be with reality and
lean into it so contemplating death
leaning into anxiety
but it's not to just feel shitty all the
time it's that you actually stop
feeling shitty when you stop running
away from parts of yourself
one good way to talk about healing is
increasing wholeness
and the dis any the dysfunctional
ways that some people interpret stoicism
are things that makes them actually
fragment
less whole they're ashamed of a part of
themselves without knowing why that
part's arising no i shouldn't feel angry
i shouldn't feel jealous repress
that and so as a result they're actually
stuffing shit into the shadows and
they're becoming more fragmented and
less whole
a healthy relationship stoically is to
say i want to understand
why that's arising what it is so that i
can incorporate it into a wholeness of
self
all right um we're approaching the
allotted 75 minutes
um do you have time for one more
question daniel or
yeah cool um so
who was that one that got a lot of plus
ones alex uh you had a really good
question
uh if you're gonna mute yourself and ask
it to daniel
uh yeah hey everyone um
so the question is daniel i've heard you
speak about how those with the greatest
depths of care often are not good at or
are not
interested in impacting the world at
scale or sort of doing what's needed
to accumulate power could you paint a
vision for how a wise empathic person
might orient to accumulating power in
the world
when i'll share how this
first occurred to me was when i was a
kid
i was engaged in part of the
homeschooling thing was i kind of got to
do the things i was interested in i was
interested in all types of activism so i
was doing
animal rights stuff with peta and
environmental stuff with greenpeace and
human rights stuff at amnesty
international because it seemed like a
meaningful life was in service to all
other life was pretty straightforward as
i was trying to figure the philosophy
out that part seemed clear
and so all of the different types of
suffering bothered me
and injustices and whatever
but i was also studying the sciences
because i wanted to understand reality
better and so i would have conversations
with scientists who would work at
military industrial complex type places
and i would get a sense of the types of
technology and sophistication they were
working with
but then advancing what types of agendas
and then be with the protesters who
were willing to undergo great harm to
themselves to stand up for what they
cared about whether they were
handcuffing themselves to old redwood to
not have it cut down or whatever
but i got to see that like picket signs
and handcuffs were the extent of the
strategic capacity
that they had compared to nsa being the
largest employer of mathematicians and
super computing technology and whatever
and i was like
10 or something when i'm like this is
the head heart divide at the level of
humanity and we go extinct as long
as those who care the most have shitty
tools for
actuation and those who have the best
tools for actuation are doing it for
narrow and divisive
ends and then a little bit later i
started to think of it as at least three
things that it was kind of mind heart
will and that any two of them
didn't really matter that there was the
development of
will and i feel like i can do something
and i'm willing to work hard to do it
and
uh values or care or compassion together
that led to an activist who really cared
about stuff and was totally willing to
work effectively but didn't have good
strategy and would just basically fail
at scale every time
then there were people who had
development of
mind and heart more but with less well
where they felt like they understood the
problems they really cared but they were
kind of like
overwhelmed crippled academics or at
best could be advisors to
powerful people that would never
actually take their advice
um and then there was kind of will in
mind together but without development of
compassion and virtue
and those were the very effective
sociopathically oriented people that ran
the world
and it was clear to me that you had to
have at least
all three of those well-developed plus
the interpersonal capacity to find other
people that had those developed and
coordinate together
to really be able to change the
trajectory of the world
and so this comes down to this whole
thing of
not being willing to suck at being in
service to
what i care about if i really
if i see the amazon burning or north
northern california burning and i see
the redwoods burning and that really
bothers me
and i am willing to continue to be
useless
towards it then i have to be like does
it really bother me do i really care
what is the fragmentation inside of
myself what does my care mean if it
doesn't predispose my
the behavior of my life what is my life
in service to if not what i care about
oh distraction or money or whatever else
i don't actually even care about what i
care about i'm just full of shit
okay that's the internal fragmentation
what does it mean to care about what i
care about it means that
my dollars and minutes will express what
i care about
then i'm acting on it but i keep failing
well then i need to look at my strategy
and say why do i keep failing
and unfortunately a lot of times people
will
work hard fail and just assess
that goliath is too big or there aren't
enough people helping
or whatever and are happy to come up
with excuses why they aren't effective
rather than really say what would it
take to be effective
because neither the ccp
nor the cia nor the kremlin just give up
and say
oh i guess we're not effective the other
guys are bigger they like keep figuring
out how to be more effective
towards their ends and so
and they can move trillions of dollars
in standing armies in the mindsets of
people
and technology as a whole if we want a
better world we have to be able to
affect the world at that level aligned
with a different value system
so what i would say is we aren't in like
game b isn't a thing really yet it's
that most kind of an idea
we live in a world that is dominated by
power
and the transition from this world to a
different kind of world system that
might have a very different culture and
governance
is only going to happen if some people
who
are authentically oriented to a
different world system learn how to
effectively move this one
and move in this one effectively
uh thank you and and i realize we're
past time so you could
either not answer this or be brief with
it i think a follow-on question
that occurs to me as i i read your piece
about the sort of
the polymath bodhisattva world creator
as sort of archetypes that represent
mind heart will um
and i feel like i have a sense of sort
of
characters or developmental pathways
that correspond with becoming a polymath
becoming a bodhisattva
but i think what's less clear and what's
kind of relevant to this question is
this notion of the archetype of a world
creator
what what does that mean and what kinds
of developmental pathways or traditions
are relevant to that
so look at people who were not born into
great wealth or power
and became very powerful and study
their biographies specifically the
biographies of their psychology and the
steps they took
and what will be interesting is you'll
be studying genghis khan and alexander
the great
napoleon and carnegie and elon musk and
whoever
and you'll be like how the fuck would i
apply some of those actually kind of
dreadful game theoretic
tactics to something better but
that's just a kind of a very superficial
assessment as you go deeper you're like
how did they empower themselves not
coming from it what were the things that
did that and what would it look like to
be able to do that towards a different
set of goals
um there's a whole big conversation here
but uh
yeah look look at people who increased
their agency
radically and then look at the
commonalities
of what is involved in increasing agency
thank you cool um
so we're going to end it here that was a
really
awesome session someone wrote in the
chat that the session really feels like
the stoa
and i i totally agree um
so yeah thank you daniel for coming out
today talk about metamodern stoicism
um any kind of uh
thoughts you'd like to share before i do
some announcements
i just love that there's a space where
these uh conversations are happening
and i'm glad to have got to be here and
i know we have another one coming up
soon
yeah yeah so uh well we'll start
plugging the
the upcoming events so the one uh next
monday the same time 7 30 p.m eastern
time
is uh daniel's coming back to do a
session on dharma inquiry so he had
these like freaking awesome questions
uh i was like what is this and then all
these people that i know are doing the
questions
like you know by themselves i'm like you
know what maybe danny would like to do a
session so
would you like to maybe speak on that a
little bit to get people
yeah i have a sense of it i wrote the
questions
because they're questions that come up
when i'm talking to people
all the time where people have a desire
to
have to figure out what their path is
what a more
meaningful life for them is and so there
is no
again algorithm for it but these are
questions that help me
kind of get a sense of that for people
um
and so anyone can just look at that and
do it on their own but what we're going
to talk about is unpacking like
when i look at those questions what am
why those questions
what is the generator function that
leads to the questions to be able to
have a sense of other questions and like
what am i looking for and
interpreting to get a sense of
um the uniqueness of someone's path
very cool um so people are asking where
they can find these questions uh if you
go to the website the store.ca and you
go rsvp to that event uh the questions
are linked
in that uh and i think you know there
might be sessions that
come from these uh these questions
because they're so rich and it takes
some time to get through them
um okay so tomorrow we have some cool
events uh jeremy johnson
is coming in tomorrow uh to do a session
critiquing let me read it for you
transcending the cancel culture critique
an integral left response
so i released this this this piece on
the cancel god and uh
some integral leftists we're critiquing
it so inviting jeremy johnson in for a
good faith critique on that that's 12
pm eastern time and then travis macy
um an ultra marathon endurance athlete
he's coming in to talk about the ultra
mindset think of like david goggins but
like a more indie version so that's
gonna be pretty cool
that's uh 6 30 p.m eastern time um
you know we have some facilitators here
uh benita bonita's back
uh do you want to plug your the hollow
uh since making a residence uh
series that you have coming up in
october
maybe shooting here okay i'm maybe
putting on your spot
um benitez can you can you hear
uh i was asking you to uh
plug the your hollow sense making uh
sense maker in residence okay sorry
i was i was out and i just came back
um so the holo the holo
is the word hollow like the
legend of sleepy hollow is a like a
riverine
place where people gathered in secret
to talk about
changing the world and
for me it's also about hollow in the
sense that
uh the zojan or the buddhist notion of
emptiness like we're hollow we're
participatory in hollow
and also halloween
uh and the the other worlds we can
we can access so yeah
i don't know i i really like that notion
of holo
um and uh
yeah the sense of moving from campfire
like which is kind of jovial to the
hollow which is
secretive and dark and riverine
uh that's kind of like what we wanna
we wanna launch and you're talking to
nora bateson
and arya back to on this thursday uh i
think yeah
we're going to talk about um
i think the energy there is like can
people stop
like stop thinking
in terms of linear cause and effect
like and then how does that
percolate into personal life
like like no if than thinking and how
how can that inform uh emergence
and yeah so
[Music]
uh that should be really exciting yeah
yeah it's going to be earth
energy a lot of energetics yeah
and so that the hollow series uh benitez
is a sense maker in residence at the
stowa for october
we have uh john robb uh dave snowden
zack stein peter wang
uh daniel gertz is coming in as well to
be a sense maker for residents for
the months of september october those
are four sessions throughout a month
uh so you can go on the website our
speaker there uh rachel haywire maybe
we'll
let you plug the last event you got the
philosopher queens
maybe you and raven can both plug it if
you guys are here
rachel haywire
raven connolly yeah yeah hi
everybody you did you go first
rachel you wanna go for it talk about
philosopher grains
yeah okay so philosopher queens are
the dark powerful feminine force that
is resurfacing as a new current i
felt a little bit of that energy just
from what the nato was saying when she
was talking about the depth and the
hollow and the expansion i definitely
felt a little bit of that energy there
so
raven and i are hosting a series here
at the stoa and in which we engage with
one another
and the people that come to the panel
and we talk about this current we talk
about
other women other philosopher queens of
history and of the present and we
bring in people to talk with them
so we're unifying the dark goddesses
cool and raven you want to plug your
socratic speed dating real brief
sure so uh yeah so psychology speed
dating happens every friday at the stoa
it's a tradition that uh peter and i
started way early back in the beginning
of the pandemic
where people can come from all aspects
of the kind of stoa ecosystem
and talk in breakup rooms that go for
about 15 minutes
and it's all spurred by a collective
intelligence of
question generation that we do as a
group so that's um yeah every friday
come join if you want to
have some personal conversation with all
the stoa faces
thank you very very cool thank you um so
if you want to continue this
conversation we we finally have a
discord you can go there that's the
invite
uh the postsense making session that's
the channel to do it and if you'd like
to support what the stowe is doing
we've done about over 300 events uh
since the the pandemic to address
a mental health crisis the the meta
crisis the meaning crisis
so you can do that on the patreon page
right there um that being said
we're going to stop recording uh we'll
have a moment of bio break and then our
boy tyson wagner is going to get some
freestyling on so if you're interested
in that you can just stay on this link
so thanks everyone and thank you daniel